Miguel Vasco

Postdoctoral Research Fellow | miguelsv@kth.se | miguelvasco.com

Division of Robotics, Perception and Learning (RPL) KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm, Sweden

RESEARCH STATEMENT

I envision a world where artificial agents perceive their environment through multiple sensors and reason over their observations to act in challenging scenarios. My research focuses on developing agents able to encode multimodal representations [S2]–[S3] and to act effectively [S1] and robustly [S4] in their environment.

Keywords: Multimodal Machine Learning · Reinforcement Learning

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

For a complete list of publications please refer to Google Scholar.

- [S1] Miguel Vasco[†], Takuma Seno[†], Kenta Kawamoto, Kaushik Subramanian, Peter R. Wurman, and Peter Stone. *A Super-human Vision-based Reinforcement Learning Agent for Autonomous Racing in Gran Turismo*. In: Proceedings of the First Reinforcement Learning Conference (RLC). vol. 1. 2024 (**Outstanding Paper Award**) [pdf]
- [S2] Petra Poklukar[†], Miguel Vasco[†], Hang Yin, Francisco S. Melo, Ana Paiva, and Danica Kragic. *Geometric Multimodal Contrastive Representation Learning*. In: Proceedings of the 39th International Conference on Machine Learning. 2022, pp. 17782–17800 [pdf]
- [S3] Miguel Vasco, Hang Yin, Francisco S. Melo, and Ana Paiva. *Leveraging hierarchy in multimodal generative models for effective cross-modality inference*. In: Neural Networks (2021 Special Issue on AI and Brain Science: Braininspired AI) 146, 2022, pp. 238–255 [pdf]
- [S4] Miguel Vasco, Hang Yin, Francisco S. Melo, and Ana Paiva. *How to Sense the World: Leveraging Hierarchy in Multimodal Perception for Robust Reinforcement Learning Agents*. In: 21st International Conference on Autonomous Agents and MultiAgent Systems (AAMAS). 2022, pp. 1301–1309 [pdf]

Note: The symbol \dagger denotes shared first-authorship.

EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Fellow KTH Royal Institute of Technology	2023–now Sweden
Game AI Research Intern Sony AI	2023 Japan
Teaching Assistant Instituto Superior Técnico, Universidade de Lisboa	2019–2022 Portugal
• Early Stage Researcher GAIPS, INESC-ID	2018–2022 <i>Portugal</i>
Visiting Researcher KTH Royal Institute of Technology	2021–2022 Sweden
Visiting Researcher National Institute of Informatics	2017–2018 Japan

EDUCATION

• Ph.D. Computer Science (Summa Cum Laude)

2018-2023

Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon, Portugal

- · Thesis Title: Multimodal Representation Learning for Agent Perception and Agency
- · Supervisors: Prof. Ana Paiva and Prof. Francisco S. Melo
- M.Sc. Engineering Physics
 Institute Superior Técnice, University of Lisber, Portugal

2013-2016

Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon, Portugal

- · Thesis Title: 3D map of the Distribution of Metals in a Cell: Applications to the Toxicity of Nanoparticles
- · Supervisors: Prof. Teresa Pinheiro and Dr. Luís Alves

Note: The symbol [†] denotes shared first-authorship.

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PAPERS (12)

- [C12] Miguel Vasco[†], Takuma Seno[†], Kenta Kawamoto, Kaushik Subramanian, Peter R. Wurman, and Peter Stone. *A Super-human Vision-based Reinforcement Learning Agent for Autonomous Racing in Gran Turismo*. In: Proceedings of the First Reinforcement Learning Conference (RLC). vol. 1. 2024 (**Outstanding Paper Award**) [pdf]
- [C11] Yuchong Zhang, Miguel Vasco, Mårten Björkman, and Danica Kragic. *Will You Participate? Exploring the Potential of Robotics Competitions on Human-Centric Topics*. In: International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction. Springer. 2024, pp. 240–255 [pdf]
- [C10] Bernardo Esteves, Miguel Vasco, and Francisco S Melo. *Pre-training with Augmentations for Efficient Transfer in Model-Based Reinforcement Learning*. In: EPIA Conference on Artificial Intelligence. Springer. 2023, pp. 133–145 [pdf]
- [C9] Nona Rajabi, Parag Khanna, Sumeyra U Demir Kanik, Elmira Yadollahi, Miguel Vasco, Mårten Björkman, Christian Smith, and Danica Kragic. *Detecting the Intention of Object Handover in Human-Robot Collaborations: An EEG Study*. In: 2023 32nd IEEE International Conference on Robot and Human Interactive Communication (ROMAN). IEEE. 2023, pp. 549–555 [pdf] [video]
- [C8] Nona Rajabi, Charles Chernik, Alfredo Reichlin, Farzaneh Taleb, Miguel Vasco, Ali Ghadirzadeh, Mårten Björkman, and Danica Kragic. *Mental Face Image Retrieval Based on a Closed-Loop Brain-Computer Interface*. In: International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction. Springer. 2023, pp. 26–45 [pdf]
- [C7] Fábio Vital, Miguel Vasco, Alberto Sardinha, and Francisco Melo. *Perceive, Represent, Generate: Translating Multimodal Information to Robotic Motion Trajectories*. In: 2022 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS). IEEE. 2022, pp. 5855–5860 [pdf]
- [C6] Petra Poklukar[†], Miguel Vasco[†], Hang Yin, Francisco S. Melo, Ana Paiva, and Danica Kragic. *Geometric Multimodal Contrastive Representation Learning*. In: Proceedings of the 39th International Conference on Machine Learning. 2022, pp. 17782–17800 (CORE A*) [pdf]
- [C5] Miguel Vasco, Hang Yin, Francisco S. Melo, and Ana Paiva. *How to Sense the World: Leveraging Hierarchy in Multimodal Perception for Robust Reinforcement Learning Agents*. In: 21st International Conference on Autonomous Agents and MultiAgent Systems (AAMAS). 2022, pp. 1301–1309 (CORE A*) [pdf]
- [C4] Pedro Ildefonso[†], Pedro Remédios[†], Rui Silva, Miguel Vasco, Francisco S. Melo, Ana Paiva, and Manuela Veloso. *Exploiting Symmetry in Human Robot-Assisted Dressing Using Reinforcement Learning*. In: EPIA Conference on Artificial Intelligence. Springer. 2021, pp. 405–417 [pdf]
- [C3] Silvia Tulli, Marta Couto, Miguel Vasco, Elmira Yadollahi, Francisco S. Melo, and Ana Paiva. *Explainable Agency by Revealing Suboptimality in Child-Robot Learning Scenarios*. In: International Conference on Social Robotics (ICSR). Springer. 2020, pp. 23–35 (**Best Student Paper Award**) [pdf]
- [C2] Rui Silva, Miguel Vasco, Francisco S. Melo, Ana Paiva, and Manuela Veloso. *Playing Games in the Dark: An Approach for Cross-Modality Transfer in Reinforcement Learning*. In: 19th International Conference on Autonomous Agents and MultiAgent Systems (AAMAS). 2020, pp. 1260–1268 (CORE A*) [pdf]
- [C1] Miguel Vasco, Francisco S. Melo, David Martins de Matos, Ana Paiva, and Tetsunari Inamura. *Learning multi-modal representations for sample-efficient recognition of human actions*. In: IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS). IEEE. 2019, pp. 4288–4293 [pdf] [slides]

JOURNAL ARTICLES (3)

- [J3] Miguel Vasco, Hang Yin, Francisco S. Melo, and Ana Paiva. *Leveraging hierarchy in multimodal generative models for effective cross-modality inference*. In: Neural Networks (2021 Special Issue on AI and Brain Science: Braininspired AI) 146, 2022, pp. 238–255 (**Scimago Q1 in Artificial Intelligence**) [pdf]
- [J2] Francisco S. Melo, Alberto Sardinha, David Belo, Marta Couto, Miguel Faria, Anabela Farias, Hugo Gamboa, Cátia Jesus, Mithun Kinarullathil, Pedro Lima, Luís Luz, André Mateus, Isabel Melo, Plinio Moreno, Daniel Osório, Ana Paiva, Jhielson Pimentel, João Rodrigues, Pedro Sequeira, Rubén Solera-Ureña, Miguel Vasco, Manuela Veloso,

and Rodrigo Ventura. *Project INSIDE: towards autonomous semi-unstructured human–robot social interaction in autism therapy.* In: Artificial intelligence in medicine 96, 2019, pp. 198–216 (**Scimago Q1 in Artificial Intelligence**) [pdf]

[J1] Miguel Vasco, Luís Cerqueira Alves, Victoria Corregidor, Daniel Correia, Cláudia P. Godinho, Isabel Sá-Correia, Andrew Bettiol, Frank Watt, and Teresa Pinheiro. *3D map distribution of metallic nanoparticles in whole cells using MeV ion microscopy*. In: Journal of Microscopy 267.2, 2017, pp. 227–236 [pdf]

REFEREED EXTENDED ABSTRACTS/WORKSHOP PAPERS (4)

- [W4] Farzaneh Taleb, Miguel Vasco, Nona Rajabi, Mårten Björkman, and Danica Kragic. *Do Foundation Models Smell Like Humans?* In: ICLR 2024 Workshop on Representational Alignment. 2024 (**CORE A***) [pdf]
- [W3] Pedro P Santos, Diogo S Carvalho, Miguel Vasco, Alberto Sardinha, Pedro A Santos, Ana Paiva, and Francisco S Melo. *Centralized Training with Hybrid Execution in Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning*. In: Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems. 2024, pp. 2453–2455 (**CORE A***) [pdf]
- [W2] Miguel Vasco. *Multimodal Representation Learning for Robotic Cross-Modality Policy Transfer*. In: Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Autonomous Agents and MultiAgent Systems (AAMAS). 2020, pp. 2225–2227 (CORE A*) [pdf] [slides] [video]
- [W1] Miguel Vasco, Francisco S. Melo, David Martins de Matos, Ana Paiva, and Tetsunari Inamura. *Online Motion Concept Learning: A Novel Algorithm for Sample-Efficient Learning and Recognition of Human Actions*. In: Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Autonomous Agents and MultiAgent Systems (AAMAS). 2019, pp. 2244–2246 (CORE A*) [pdf] [poster]

PREPRINTS (3)

- [P3] Bernardo Esteves, Miguel Vasco, and Francisco S Melo. *NeuralThink: Algorithm Synthesis that Extrapolates in General Tasks*. In: arXiv preprint arXiv:2402.15393, 2024 [pdf]
- [P2] Alfredo Reichlin, Miguel Vasco, Hang Yin, and Danica Kragic. *Goal-Conditioned Offline Reinforcement Learning via Metric Learning*. In: arXiv preprint arXiv:2402.10820, 2024 [pdf]
- [P1] Miguel Vasco, Francisco S. Melo, and Ana Paiva. MHVAE: a Human-inspired Deep Hierarchical Generative Model for Multimodal Representation Learning. In: arXiv preprint arXiv:2006.02991, 2020 [pdf]

RESEARCH PROJECTS

• ELSA (EU Horizon 2020) Researcher

2023-now

- ELSA is a virtual center of excellence that will spearhead efforts in foundational safe and secure artificial intelligence (AI) methodology research. A large and growing network of top European experts in AI and machine learning is to promote the development and deployment of cutting-edge AI solutions in the future and make Europe the world's lighthouse of AI.
- · I am part of the KTH group, developing benchmarks for privacy-preserving learning and human-in-the-loop learning in robotics.
- TAILOR (EU Horizon 2020, GA. No.952215)

 Researcher

2021-2023

- The purpose of TAILOR is to build a strong academic-public-industrial research network with the capacity of providing the scientific basis for Trustworthy AI leveraging and combining learning, optimization and reasoning for realizing AI systems that incorporate the safeguards that make them in the reliable, safe, transparent and respectful of human agency and expectations.
- · I was part of the research team of Técnico, and my research focused on the development of model-based RL agents in multimodal environments.
- RELEvaNT (Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia, ref. PTDC/CCI-COM/5060/2021)
 Researcher

2021-2023

- · RELEvaNT investigates new models and methods for efficient deep RL in non-stationary environments and the potential applications on several "human-centered" domains.
- · I was part of the research team of INESC-ID, and my research focused on the creation of the representation models for model-based RL agents in multimodal scenarios with partial-observability settings.
- INSIDE (CMU-Portugal Program, ref. CMUP-ERI/HCI/0051/2013)
 Researcher

- · INSIDE investigated the development of symbiotic human-robot interaction and its applications in the therapy of children with impaired development. The project included the deployment of actual robots in an hospital environment and its autonomous intervention in therapy sessions with children with autism spectrum disorders (ASD).
- In this project I was part of the research team of INESC-ID, and my research focused on the creation of the computational framework for the decision-making and animation systems of an autonomous mobile robot.

INVITED TALKS AND CONSORTIA

 Multimodal Representations for Perceiving and Acting Shizuoka University, Japan. 	2023
 Multimodal Representation Learning for Agent Perception and Agency Robotics Perception Learning group, KTH Royal Institute of Technology. 	2021
 Multimodal Representation Learning for Robot Perception and Agency RSS Pioneers – [poster] 	2021
 Multimodal Representation Learning for Robotic Cross-Modality Policy Transfer AAMAS Doctoral Consortium – [slides] [video] 	2020

HONORS AND DISTINCTIONS

Best PhD Thesis in AI Award	2024
Awarded by the Portuguese Association for Artificial Intelligence (APPIA).	

Best Paper Awards

Reinforcement Learning Conference (RLC), 2024 - [C12], International Conference on Social Robotics (ICSR), 2020 - [C3].

· RSS Pioneer 2021

Selective annual workshop in the "Robotics: Science and Systems" conference.

· Cohort of the AAMAS Doctoral Consortium 2020

Selective annual workshop in the "International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems".

2020, 2021 · Excellence in Teaching Award, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon Annual award given to "teachers who stood out for their pedagogical excellence".

2022 Sony AI Scholarship Awarded to attend the 4th International Summer School on Artificial Intelligence and Games

2018 Ph.D. Grant

Awarded by 'Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia", ref. SFRH/BD/139362/2018.

· Research Grant 2017, 2022 Awarded in Project INSIDE and Project RELEvaNT by INESC-ID.

TEACHING AND SUPERVISION

COURSES

FDD3359 Reinforcement Learning

Spring 2024

Doctoral Programme at the School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (EECS)

KTH Royal Institute of Technology

- · Role: Teacher
- · Main lecturer, responsible for the organization and creation of contents for the course.
- DD2430 Project Course in Data Science

Fall 2023

Master Degree in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

KTH Royal Institute of Technology

- · Role: Teaching Assistant
- · Helping students develop their research projects in collaboration with industry partners.
- · Planning, Learning and Intelligent Decision-Making

2021-2022

Master Degree in Computer Science and Engineering, Master Degree in Data Science

Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon

- · Role: Teaching Assistant
- · Supervising lab sessions, grading student labs
- · Student Evaluation: 9.0/9.0 (2021)
- · Excellency in Teaching Award: 2021

· Computation and Society (AI Ethics)

2019-2020

Undergraduate Degree in Computer Science and Engineering

Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon

- · Role: Teaching Assistant
- · Discussing current ethical issues in AI, grading student presentations;

M.Sc. Computer Science, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon

- · Student Evaluation: 8.4/9.0 (2019), 9.0/9.0 (2020)
- · Excellency in Teaching Award: 2020

PH.D. STUDENTS

•	Alfredo Reichlin, "Interactive Representation Learning"	2023-now
	Doctoral Programme at the School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, KTH Royal Institute of Technology	
	Co-advised with Danica Kragic and Hang Yin	

Bernardo Esteves, "Learning to Act at Scale: Algorithm Synthesis using Deep Neural Networks"
 Doctoral Programme in Computer Science, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon
 Co-advised with Francisco S. Melo

2023-now

• Farzaneh Taleb, "Evaluating Representational Alignment in Natural and Artificial Intelligent Systems"

Doctoral Programme at the School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, KTH Royal Institute of Technology
Co-advised with Danica Kragic and Mårten Björkman

2023-now

Nona Rajabi, "Extracting Human Intention and Perception from Physiological Signals using Data-driven Models" 2023-now
Doctoral Programme at the School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, KTH Royal Institute of Technology
Co-advised with Danica Kragic and Mårten Björkman

M.SC. STUDENTS

•	 Afonso Fernandes, "Using Multi-modal Generative Models against Adversarial Perceptual Attacks to RL Agents" 	2023
	M.Sc. Computer Science, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon	
	Bernardo Esteves, "Efficient pre-training in model-based reinforcement learning"	2021
	M.Sc. Computer Science, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon	
	• Fábio Vital, "Deep generative models for model-based reinforcement learning."	2021

OTHER SUPERVISION ROLES

• Adriano Pacciarelli, Research Engineer	2024-now
KTH Royal Institute of Technology	
Pedro Ildefonso, Summer internships of INESC-ID,	2019
Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon	
Pedro Remédios, Summer Internships of INESC-ID	2019
Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon	

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

ORGANIZATIONAL ROLES

• Multimodal Representation Learning: Perks and Pitfalls Workshop (ICLR) – Organizer [website]	2023
RSS Pioneers Workshop – Faculty Chair [website]	2022

REVIEWER

Journals

Entertainment Computing	2022
Neural Computing and Applications	2020–2022

Conferences

Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)	2024
European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI)	2024
International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)	2022-2023
International Symposium of Robotic Research (ISRR)	2022
ACM International Conference on Intelligent Virtual Agents (IVA)	2022
 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) 	2020, 2022-2023
AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)	2020-2024

Workshop:

Workshops	
HRI Pioneers Workshop (HRI) – [website]	2021–2023
• Adaptive and Learning Agents Workshop (AAMAS) – [website]	2020–2023
Other	
ELLIS Evaluator	2021, 2022
RESEARCH COMMUNITY SERVICE	
• RPL Summer School on Robotics, Perception and Learning	2024
Organiser of the RPL Summer School on Robotics, Perception and Learning at Stockholm, Sweden – [website]	2020 2022
• Talking Robotics Co-founder of the online bi-weekly virtual seminars about robotics and adjacent fields – [website] [twitter] [youtube]	2020–2023
· Goal: Provide visibility and network opportunities for early-career researchers in AI and Robotics.	
· Co-founders: Patrícia Alves-Oliveira, Joana Campos and Silvia Tulli.	
· Sponsors: Semio and PAL Robotics.	
Robotics Reading Group	2019–2020
Organizer of the Robotics Reading Group at Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon – [website]	
MEDIA COVERAGE	
• New Scientist – online article about our super-human vision-based racing agent for Gran Turismo 7 [S1].	2024
 Robohub – online article featured multiple sessions of Talking Robotics. 	2021
• Synced Review – online article about our AAMAS paper [S4];	2019

• Correio da Manhã – TV report about the impact of robotics in therapy of children, referencing Project INSIDE;

• Diário de Notícias – magazine article about recent developments in robotics, referencing Project INSIDE.

REFERENCES

• Danica Kragic, KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Sweden

dani@kth.se

2018

2018

· Ana Paiva, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon, Portugal

ana.paiva@inesc-id.pt

· Francisco S. Melo, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon, Portugal

fmelo@inesc-id.pt